CV Data

Personal Information

Name: SAHIL ZUTSHI (D.O.B 29/11/1983, British Citizen)
Contact: Email: sahil@zutshi.me, Phone: +44 (0)7581146555

Specialisations: Transport & Development Planning, Transport Engineering and Modelling

Languages: English, Hindi, Urdu, Basic Spanish

Synopsis

Sahil is a Transport Engineer/Planner with over six years of experience having worked at consultancies in Transport Planning and Development Control in England.

His work involves the production of Transport Assessments (TAs), Statements (TSs) and Technical Reports on a variety of Transportation and Highways related issues for clients from the private and public sector. These have involved the comprehensive review of the development of land and property, with particular emphasis on quantifying the impact of a proposal on the existing transport and highway infrastructure and identifying suitable mitigation options resulting in schemes capable of meeting the requirements of the Local Planning Authority.

The work also involves the identification of development constraints by highlighting them at an early stage to enable the project team to address them in a proactive manner, including the mitigation of problems both on and off site. He attends client, local authority, planning and design team meetings on a regular basis and has been assigned project management duties on a number of projects. The work has required skills for undertaking a range of work including master planning of large schemes, feasibility assessments, scoping studies, traffic management, traffic growth forecasting, junction assessments, site investigations, parking strategies, accessibility planning and modeling, policy work, data collection and analysis and advice on legal agreements relating to planning obligations and conditions. These projects have improved his knowledge in applying the methods outlined in the Design Manual for Roads and Bridges (DMRB) and following WebTAG, guidance, as well as improving his knowledge of the planning procedure and regulatory system.

Sahil is numerate and has experience in the use of a range of software packages specific to the transport industry such as ARCADY 5-8, PICADY 5, JUNCTIONS 8, LinSig 3, TRANSYT 14, S-PARAMICS, PARAMICS Discovery, TRICS, TRAVL, TEMPRO, ACCESSION and ArcGIS.

He possesses excellent written and verbal communication skills which have been enhanced through accomplishing academic, work projects and constant liaising with different departments and clients at the workplace. He holds a CSCS card, is CRB checked and committed to continuous professional development and working towards becoming a Chartered Engineer.

Previously, Sahil worked at the Environment Agency and has had experience working in environmental sector, flood risk management, EIA and regeneration projects.

Good humoured and calm, he is seeking a suitable environment where these characteristics and experience can be used to optimal effect. His interests include travelling, astronomy, music, sports and reading.

Employment

October 2012 -Present Transport Engineer/Planner – Self Employed

- After undertaking a sabbatical, was involved with freelance consulting work.
- Was involved in a research project for the Government of Rajasthan, India, to assist with the construction of a multi-modal transport model for Mount Abu as part of the overall master-planning and rezoning of the conurbation. A zonal movement model was developed for a proposed 500 hectare new town. This was then used to determine transport infrastructure provision for the overall development. In addition to roads, cycling and walking routes were also identified. The public transport infrastructure included the use of a proposed rapid transit system serving several functions, including a leisure role, by integrating the base station adjacent to existing bus infrastructure in the nearby towns of Shivganj, Swaroopganj, Ambaji and Sirohi.

June 2009-September 2012 Cundall (formerly Cundall Johnston & Partners LLP), Newcastle upon Tyne, UK. Transport Engineer

- Involved with producing Transport Assessments, Transport Statements, Travel Plans and a variety of transport related studies/reports.
- Project management and responsible for the successful delivery of projects.
- Working closely with Principle Engineers, Associates and the Business Partner to cover all aspects of projects. Regularly attend clients, local authority, planning, design and other project related meetings.
- Liaising with high profile clients from the public and private sector on a daily basis and also maintaining client relationships.

July 2007-April 2009

Mouchel Group (formerly Mouchel Parkman), Surrey, UK.
Development Planning & Control, Transport Planning, South.
Transport Planner (promotion from Graduate Transport Planner)

- Successfully joined the company via the structured 'Graduate Development Programme' to gain experience in an assortment of transport planning and engineering related projects for clients with public and private sectors.
- Involved with Transport Assessments, Travel Plans advice (Smarter Choices initiative) and frameworks, Feasibility studies, Master-planning, Junction capacity assessments and modelling, detailed traffic data and accident data analysis, analysis of network traffic flows and forecasting using NRTF factors, Trip rate generation and analysis, Site visits and investigation for scoping and baseline studies, RSI survey logic checks on GIS software, Parking review studies, Accessibility studies (PTALs) and production of Isochromes, Elementary COBA economics and sensitivity tests.
- Made use of a range of documents such as PPG13, Planning Policy Statements, LDF's and LTP's to undertake planning policy work and referring to other guidance documents such as the DMRB, Manual for Streets etc.
- Gained experience is using a range of software packages used for civil and transport planning applications including ARCADY, PICADY, LINSIG, TRICS, TRAVL, TEMPRO, and AutoCAD.
- Preparing invoices to be sent to clients, completing CDM forms, and worked closely with the divisional coordinator for all matters relating to Quality Management Systems (QMS).

July 2006-April 2007 Environment Agency, Hatfield, Hertfordshire, UK. Project Assistant, Flood Risk Management & Data Management

- Was part of a busy team at the Thames Region Office responsible for matters relating
 to flood management for the Thames Region and reviewing a variety of surveys including
 Asset & Site Survey Reports, Topographical Surveys & Maps, Law Enforcement &
 Prosecution files containing sensitive information.
- Was responsible for updating the structure of the computer filing system, reviewing
 existing files, creating file inventories and managing the database. Assisted in promoting
 new procedures for record management in all departments of the agency.

June 2002-November 2005

UCI 9 Screens Multiplex Cinemas, Hatfield, UK. Assistant Manager & Team Leader (Promotion)

- Responsible for the operational success of one of the busiest and profitable cinemas in the UK. Operational manager on shift responsible for managing staff members.
- Stock control (shrinkages & damages), stock delivery, count, forecasting and ordering.
 Cashing-up operations Close-out. Accountable and experienced in conducting weekly internal management and cash audits.
- Frontline customer service and meeting business needs. Responsible for Staff recruitment, training and development.

Education, Qualifications and Professional Status

Qualification	Course of Study or Professional grade	Awarding body	Year awarded
BSc (Hons)	Environmental Management	University of Hertfordshire	2006
DipBA	Business Administration	College of Technology, London	2005
Certificate	Course in Traffic and Transportation	PTRC (Planning and Transport, Research and Computation)	2009
GCE "A" Levels	The British Council	Edecxel, University of London	2001
ICSE	Schooling (1993-2000)	Rishi Valley School, KFI	2000
MCIHT	Member	The Chartered Institution of Highways and Transportation	2009
MIHE	Member	Institution of Highways Engineers	2009

Selective Project Experience / Managerial Roles

Residential

Client David Wilson Homes North East (Barratt Homes) 2010-2012
Project Grey Towers Farm Residential Development, Nunthorpe

Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Responsible for the production and successful delivery of a TA for the planning permission for a controversial 300 dwelling 'executive' housing development on a Greenfield site, located on the outskirts of Nunthorpe, Middlesbrough. Detailed discussions were held with the Council and the Highways Agency over months to discuss mitigation measures on a fully saturated corridor route. Traffic generation was determined from undertaking a survey at a site composed of similar housing in the area and distribution was based on the HA's assessment and the Council's area-wide TRIPS model. The development impact was assessed utilising the Council's AIMSUN micro-simulation corridor model, as well as ARCADY/PICADY. Numerous design option and scenarios were presented as mitigation measures to the design team over a period of six months. Two public consultation were organised which were particularly challenging due sensitive traffic issues in the local area and strong local opposition for the scheme.

Client Dunelm Homes 2010-2011

Project The Middles, Stanley

Role Project Manager, Transport Engineer

Responsible for the preparation of a TA to accompany the planning application for 285 dwellings. The site previously obtained planning permission for 210 dwellings, with the permission soon expiring the scheme involved detailed discussions with the HA as the original application was not referred to the HA by the LPA. Detailed gravity modelling was undertaken for the HA to demonstrate that the impact of the development was minimal on the SRN. Was also responsible for providing transportation advice relating to accessibility and permeability of the site to the design team.

Workplace

Client 1NewcastleGateshead (1NG) 2009-2010

Project Toffee Factory, Newcastle upon Tyne
Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Responsible for the production of a TA to support the planning permission of the redevelopment of a former industrial site for office use for the creative industry as part of the Ouseburn Valley regeneration. Involved in providing traffic and transportation advice to the client and the design team, which included the design of a new site access. Prepared and discussed the scoping study for the TA with the Highways Dept. at the Council and attended regular design team and planning meetings.

Retail

Client Rockspring Property, Manse 2010-2011

Project Blaydon Town Centre Regeneration
Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Responsible for the production of the TA to accompany to planning application for the redevelopment of Blaydon Centre. Involved in providing traffic and transportation advice to the client and the design team, which included the design of a new site access. The focus of the TA was to assess the current car parking utilisation at the Centre and determine whether current provision were adequate to accommodate the likely traffic generated from the proposed expansion. A large network made up of complex junctions was also assessed for capacity.

Leisure/Lifestyle

Client The Aln Valley Railway Trust, Duke of Northumerbland 2009-2010

Project Aln Valley Railway, Alnwick

Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Project Manager and Engineer responsible for the preparation of a full TA to accompany the planning application for the re-use of the former historic railway line/track bed and the construction of a railways terminus adjacent to an industrial estate and to the A1. The project involved extensive discussions with the Highways Agency and Northumberland Council. Traffic generation and parking was calculated from first principle basis due to the unique operational requirements of the development.

Client Orchestrator Ltd. 2009

Project Orchestrator LARP (Live Action Role Play), Durham

Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Project Manager and Engineer involved in site visits, negotiations with the local authority and the successful delivery of feasibility report involving junction assessments over a large network and a comprehensive review of proposed options. Also, part of the brief was to provide the client with estimated costs for junction improvements where required. First principles were used for both traffic generation and car parking requirements due to the unique operational requirements of the development.

Education

Client Suffolk County Council, Gleeds Advisory Ltd. 2009-2010

Project Suffolk CC BSF (Building Schools for the Future) Ipswich &

Felixstowe

Role Project Manager, Transportation Engineer

Engineer responsible for the preparation of Transport Assessments and Statements for 5 sites within Suffolk. This involves the provision of transportation advice for several options on site layout design, accessibility options for both staff and pupils, servicing arrangements, traffic data analysis, distribution and assignment, highway impact and capacity assessments using industry approved software.

2009-2010

Client London Borough of Ealing, Balfour Beatty.
Project Ealing BSF (Building Schools for the Future)

Role Transportation Engineer

Produced two TS's to support the planning permission of the redevelopment of Cardinal Wiseman School and Dormer Wells School in Ealing, London. The project involved lengthy discussion and analysis to assure the local highway authority that the introduction of a layby will not have a detrimental impact upon the capacity and operation of the adjacent road. Carried out site visit to identify highway accessibility issues and carried out a sustainability transport audit and a PTAL study. Assessment of development traffic generation and distribution of vehicles carrying waste and recycling to local and strategic highway network was also carried out. Junctions that would be most affected were identified and tested for capacity assessments.

Health

Client Ramsay Health Care Limited 2009-2010

Project Cobalt NHS Treatment Centre, Newcastle upon Tyne

Role Transportation Engineer

Engineer involved with the provision of traffic and transportation advice for the proposal to extend the existing day case surgical facility to an Inpatient Surgical facility within the Cobalt Business Park Complex in North Tyneside. This involved assessing seven junctions in the area of influence that included the A19 Holystone Roundabout currently maintained by the Highways Agency.

Client PRP Architects 2009
Project Yarm Medical Centre

Role Transportation Engineer

A detailed TA was prepared which involved junction capacity assessments. Parking assessment was a key issue for this development as the Councils standards resulted in the scheme being unviable. Primary and secondary data was used to demonstrate that the quantum of development could be accommodated without detriment. The development was granted planning permission. A TP was provided which also accompanied the planning application.